<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Jasmin Rubinovitz</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz" />
<updated>2015-12-15T14:01:50-05:00</updated>
<id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/</id>
<author>
  <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
  <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/</uri>
  <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bike Helmet]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/final-project/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/final-project</id>
  <published>2015-12-15T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-12-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;idea&quot;&gt;Idea&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When commuting with my bicycle at night, I feel almost invisible, and very unsafe. Also, many time I find myself hoping I could signal the cars and riders around me that I am about to stop or turn.  These reasons are what made me make my smart bike helmet, I also thought that this helmet could be a great integration of all the different thing I learned through the semester and a way to learn some more.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	 &lt;figcaption&gt;The bike helmet I designed during the [first week](../week1-computer-aided-design/index.html) when thinking of a final project.&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cardboardtech.com/&quot;&gt;cardboard bicycle&lt;/a&gt; made 2 years ago in israel. If you can make an entire bike out of cardboard and ride it safely, could you make a eco friendly helmet to fit?&lt;br /&gt;
 I then found out that someone as already thought about this before me - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kraniums.com/&quot;&gt;Kraniums&lt;/a&gt; and they are selling a cardboard helmet that has proved to be safer than some rigid foam helmets.&lt;br /&gt;
 This led me to the decision that the skeleton for my helmet will be laser cut cardboard - it is light, safe, and easy to make.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I measured my head and as a first test made an half ellipsoid and cut it out. this worked great, so I used Rhino to design a nicer looking helmet.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	 &lt;figcaption&gt;The helmet I designed&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used a great Grasshopper script I found &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.grasshopper3d.com/forum/topics/a-solid-waffle-for-laser&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to create waffle construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;making-the-helmet&quot;&gt;Making The Helmet&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started by laser cutting cardboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	 &lt;figcaption&gt;Laser cutting the helmet parts&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After construction the helmet together and trying it out, I decided I need to make a rigid top for it.
&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/half_elipsoid_helmet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/cardboard_sizes_and_shapes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/laser_cut_cardboard.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	 &amp;lt;figcaption&amp;gt;Trying out the cardboard helmet.&amp;lt;/figcaption&amp;gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first decided to try composites. This is explained more on composite week page (added soon).&lt;br /&gt;
Here are some pictures of the process:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/composites_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/composites_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/composites_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	 &amp;lt;figcaption&amp;gt;Making composites on top of the cardboard helmet&amp;lt;/figcaption&amp;gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	 &amp;lt;figcaption&amp;gt;composites results&amp;lt;/figcaption&amp;gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was a really strong helmet (I could even easily stand on it, as seen in the pictures above) but I did not like the look of the burlap, and also wanted a cover that is clear, so I can add the LEDs under it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I than went on to try vacuum forming.&lt;br /&gt;
For doing vacuum forming, you have to have a mold.  Since I wanted to use thing that were in our inventory, I decided to CNC foam.  The largest tool head in the shop that could mill the foam was 5” long. So I have to cut my model in half, and machine to pieces of 4” foam. (I glued together 2 block of foam using super 77 glue).
&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/cnc_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/cnc_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/cnc_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	 &amp;lt;figcaption&amp;gt;Machining the foam to make my mold&amp;lt;/figcaption&amp;gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/cnc_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/cnc_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/cnc_6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vacuum forming is a really quick and simple process, but it’s also a kind of art. You heat up a piece o PTEG plastic, laid above your mold,  when it’s hot enough, you take to mold up and turn on the vacuum. the hot plastic becomes flexible and get the shape of your mold.
The hardest part is knowing exactly when the plastic is ready. If it’s not hot enough it will not be pulled all the way on the mold. If it’s too hot, it become too wide, and you get wrinkles and a mess. The difference between not hot enough and too hot is a matter of seconds. John knew it best.
Another thing we’ve learned is that vacuum forming foam is not the best Idea. The foam gets hot and changes it shape, I also stick to the plastic.
For preventing the sticking, I covered the mold with Gesso and let it dry, I then sprayed a lot of resales on it before every vacuum forming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	 &lt;figcaption&gt;Vacuum forming the helmet mold.&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not consider the shrinking of the foam during the vacuum forming. This was a problem since the plastic helmet was too small and could not fit on the cardboard. For the plastic to fit on the cardboard helmet and the helmet to also fit on my head, I had to make it really thin. My original design was 3 cm thick, the this design was 1cm thick, this was much less strong and I would only want to use the thin helmet as a last resource.
Instead, I tried to vacuum form again, this time on a cardboard model, a little bit bigger than the helmet I would really use.&lt;br /&gt;
I used paper mache to cover the helmet from the outside. Since I already used this technique for the composites, I knew the paper with the glue will be strong enough to handle the vacuum forces.
I cut brown paper in pieces, and glued them on top of the helmet using All-purpose glue that I miked with a little bit of water. it’s very important that the entire piece will be covered in glue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Cardboard and paper mache vacuum forming mold.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I again sprayed a lot of release on the model.
&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&amp;lt;figcaption&amp;gt; Vacuum forming the cardboard mold&amp;lt;/figcaption&amp;gt;
&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried the cardboard mold twice, the first time, it was just a little bit to cold. and did not go all the was to the edges of the mold. The second time it was way too hat, I sticked to my model and I had to throw it away. I took the almost perfect one and later used a heat gun to fit it completely on my cardboard base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Using heat gun to fit the plastic.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;electronics&quot;&gt;Electronics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electronics part was done in parallel to the making of the helmet itself. I started out by making a small breakout board for the LSM303 - The accelerometer and compass sensor. I thought the having a compass in my helmet can be useful for other cool implementations and wanted to try it out.&lt;br /&gt;
 I used the Application hints from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.st.com/web/en/resource/technical/document/datasheet/DM00027543.pdf&quot;&gt;LSM303 datasheet&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Application hints from the data sheet.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we don’t have 4.7uF and 0.22uF capacitors in the inventory I used 2 .1uF capacitors in parallel to get .2uF, and 2 10 uF capacitors in series to get 5 uF. I designed the board in Eagle leaving large SMD pads to connect power, GND, SCL,SDA, INT1 and INT2.&lt;br /&gt;
I also added a 3.3V regulator, do no matter what power is connected, the accelerometer always get 3.3V (Analog supply voltage 2.16 V to 3.6 V specified in the datasheet)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Eagle schematics&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; the board I sent for milling&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; breakout board with components soldered.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used Neil’s reflow method to solder the tiny accelerometer component.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I than tested this using a Sparkfun RedBoard (Arduino Uno compatible) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adafruit/Adafruit_LSM303&quot;&gt;Adafruit’s LSM303 Library&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
At the first try, nothing printed to the serial port and I was very disappointed. I tested the board using a multimeter and everything seemed fine. One of the TA’s suggested that the accelerometer is not soldered to the board correctly. I used to heat gun again and pressed the component the the board really hard this time, from all it’s sides.&lt;br /&gt;
This did the trick and this time I got values printing, corresponding the the location and acceleration of the board :).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then went on the design the main control board. I knew I would have to use a few Arduino libraries that will probably take a lot of space, so the ATtiny84 with 8 Kbytes flash memory will not be enough.
After some research about different ATMega controllers and ATxmege, I decided to use the ATMeag328P, which was in the inventory, and is also used in Neil’s  &lt;a href=&quot;http://academy.cba.mit.edu/classes/embedded_programming/index.html&quot;&gt;hello.arduino.328P board&lt;/a&gt; that I could use as a reference for designing my board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As output LEDs I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adafruit.com/products/1138&quot;&gt;Adafruit NeoPixel Digital RGB LED Strip&lt;/a&gt; which is a strip of RGB LED that are separately addressable controlled by only one digital output pin.
Adafruit website recommends using a large capacitor between VCC and GND for the LEDs, I used the larges SMD capacitor I could find which was 220 uF.
I added connections to SDA and SCL so I could speak to the accelerometer and also used 3 digital pines for 2 capacitive touch surfaces, that will control the turning lights. (one pin for send and 2 pines for receive.) I used 5M resistors between the send and receive pins.
Also added a lithium battery connector and an ON/OFF slider switch. I also added one connection the one Analog pin but I ended up not using this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Eagle schematics&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; the board I sent for milling&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/final/placeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Soldering the ATMega, (I ruined the first one. Then I first put solder on the copper traces and the refolwed it with the soldering iron one each leg.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/final-project/&quot;&gt;The Bike Helmet&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on December 15, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interface and Application Programming]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week11-interface-programming/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week11-interface-programming</id>
  <published>2015-12-02T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-12-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;button-input-and-led-control&quot;&gt;Button input and LED Control&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week11/open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week’s assignment was to  write an application that interfaces with an input or output device that we made.&lt;br /&gt;
I’ve decided to use the board I made on &lt;a href=&quot;../week6-electronics-design/index.html&quot;&gt;week 6&lt;/a&gt; which has an input device (a button), an output device (red LED) and a way to communicate with a serial port (FTDI header).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week11/board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; My board from week 6, with FTDI, LED and a button&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href=&quot;../week8-embedded-programming/index.html&quot;&gt;week 8&lt;/a&gt; I added a bluetooth module to this board and was interested in writing an interface for that as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;programming-the-board&quot;&gt;Programming the board&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to make an interface for the board, I had to also program the board itself.
Since my board has an FTDI header on it. I am using serial communication for sending and receiving data from the board.
(I’m using the Arduino &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arduino.cc/en/Reference/SoftwareSerial&quot;&gt;SoftwareSerial library&lt;/a&gt;)  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board programming is not separate from the interface programming, and I iterated over this until I got the board to do exactly what I want. (programming the board, developing the interface, changing both…)
The board I programmed to send ‘0’ when the button is not pressed and ‘1’ when the button is pressed.&lt;br /&gt;
Also, it turns on the LED when ‘1’ is sent, turns it off when ‘0’ is sent and blinks it when ‘2’ is sent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the Arduino Serial Monitor to test my code. (This is the magnitude glass icon on the top left of the window)  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arduino code looks like that:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-c--&quot; data-lang=&quot;c++&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#include &amp;lt;SoftwareSerial.h&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define LED            7                &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// The digital connector port to LED anode&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define BUTTON         3                &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// The digital connector port to the button&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledState&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boolean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;blink_state&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;previousMillis&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// will store last time LED was updated&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;interval&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;500&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
 
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;SoftwareSerial&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;mySerial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// RX, TX &lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pinMode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;OUTPUT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;                  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Set the LED output&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pinMode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;BUTTON&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;INPUT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;                &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Set the button input&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;                &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Turn off the LED&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mySerial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;   				 &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Init the serial port&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;loop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalRead&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;BUTTON&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// if the button is pressed  if (digitalRead(BUTTON) == HIGH) { // if the button is pressed&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mySerial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mySerial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;byte&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mySerial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;available&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// if there is data available on the serial port&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mySerial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;read&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sc&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;1&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;blink_state&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sc&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;2&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;blink_state&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;blink_state&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;currentMillis&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;millis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;currentMillis&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;previousMillis&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;interval&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// save the last time you blinked the LED&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;previousMillis&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;currentMillis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// if the LED is off turn it on and vice-versa:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;blink_state&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledState&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledState&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledState&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// set the LED with the ledState of the variable:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;javascript-and-html-interface-programming&quot;&gt;Javascript and HTML interface programming&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to try and use javascript and HTML for the initial programming, due to a number of reasons:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The other good option was python, which I already used a lot in the past, and I wanted to learn something new.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have other projects that require web development and this was a good opportunity to improve my skills.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wanted to later make this a mobile app that controls the board through Bluetooth and web development is a good starting point for later using &lt;a href=&quot;http://ionicframework.com/&quot;&gt;Ionic&lt;/a&gt;, which I also wanted to try.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming the web interface was pretty straight forward using Neil’s magnet example.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;boardhtml-file&quot;&gt;board.html file:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;content&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;button&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;button&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;onclick=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;turnOn()&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Turn on!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;button&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;itype=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;button&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;onclick=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;turnOff()&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Turn off!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;button&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;itype=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;button&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;onclick=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;blink()&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Blink!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;script &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;application/javascript&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;rect&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;rect&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;text&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;server&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;127.0.0.1:1234&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;socket&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;WebSocket&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;ws://&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;server&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;socket&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;onopen&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;connected to &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;server&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;socket&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;onerror&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;can&amp;#39;t connect to &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;server&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;socket&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;onmessage&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;0&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;?&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Not pressed&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Pressed!&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;querySelector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;.content&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;innerHTML&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;turnOn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;socket&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;1&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;blink&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;socket&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;2&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;turnOff&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;socket&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;0&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;boardjs-file&quot;&gt;board.js file:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;server_port&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;1234&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;client_address&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;127.0.0.1&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// This should match the serial port that you board is connected to&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;serial_port&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;/dev/cu.usbserial-FTHBRJSI&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;baud&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9600&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;samples&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// open serial port&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;SerialPort&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;serialport&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;SerialPort&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;sp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;SerialPort&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;serial_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;baudrate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;baud&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;sp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;can not open &amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;serial_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;opened &amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;serial_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;sp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;data&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
         &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;stringify&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]));&lt;/span&gt;
         &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;listening for connections from &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;client_address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot; on &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;server_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;Server&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;ws&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;Server&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;wss&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;Server&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;server_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;wss&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;connection&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ws&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ws&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;_socket&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;remoteAddress&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;client_address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;error: client address doesn&amp;#39;t match&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;connected to &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;client_address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot; on port &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;server_port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

   &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// when recieving data from the websocket, send it to the serial port  &lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ws&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;message&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;received: %s&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;sp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

   &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// when recieving data from serial port - send it to the web socket&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;sp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;data&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ws&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;stringify&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]));&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

   &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For running this you have to install &lt;a href=&quot;https://nodejs.org/en/&quot;&gt;Node.js&lt;/a&gt; 
And also websocket and serial port packages: &lt;code&gt;npm install ws and serialport&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You then run &lt;code&gt;node board.js&lt;/code&gt; from the command line and open the board.html file in you favorite browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks like that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week11/screen.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Controlling the board from the html window on my computer&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this simple interface I can see the button state and control the LED. This is just a simple “Hello world” app for my board. The possibilities are endless and I had many ideas such as a game testing your reaction time to random LED blinking, and playing music and drawing using only the button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really wanted to try and write a mobile app that controls my board via Bluetooth so I left this simple at the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-mobile-app-using-bluetooth&quot;&gt;A mobile app using Bluetooth.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never wrote a mobile app before and this week was a great opportunity to learn a little bit about that and try using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ionicframework.com/&quot;&gt;Ionic Framework&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As, mentioned, during &lt;a href=&quot;../week8-embedded-programming/index.html&quot;&gt;week 8&lt;/a&gt;, I made an adapter that connects my board’s serial port to a Bluetooth module (an HM-10 BLE, BLE stands for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetooth_low_energy&quot;&gt;Bluetooth Low Energy&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week11/module.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; board from [week 8](../week8-embedded-programming/index.html) connected to a bluetooth module&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I used a Bluetooth app to see if i can send and receive data to my board via bluetooth.&lt;br /&gt;
I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/lightblue/id639944780?mt=12&quot;&gt;Light blue&lt;/a&gt; which is a mac app, but there are plenty of similar applications for different OS and also for mobile devices.
I connected to HMSoft and sent ‘0’, ‘1’, ‘2’ to the board, this functioned as expected so I continued. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then started developing my app.&lt;br /&gt;
Since I never used ionic before, I started with watching this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C-UwOWB9Io4&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;20 min Ionic crah cours video&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, I searched online for examples using Ionic and a bluetooth serial port, there are many different plugins for that.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this example :&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/don/ionic-ble&quot;&gt;https://github.com/don/ionic-ble&lt;/a&gt; and tested it on my phone, it worked and this plugin includes all the BLE functions I needed so I decided to use that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I changed the interface and added buttons that sends messages to the board, and also constantly receiving notifications from it while connected.
The code can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasrub/ionic-ble&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.14/people/tomer_weller/index.html&quot;&gt;Tomer&lt;/a&gt; helped me a lot in debugging this and figuring out what exactly I should send to the bluetooth (A string converted to an ArrayBuffer).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final result is a cute mobile app that can connect to the HMSoft and send “Turn On”, “Turn Off” or “Blink” commands to it.
When the button on the board is pressed the background of the app becomes red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week11/red.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Pressing the button makes app background red&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week11/app.gif&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also a very simple app but it took me a long time to figure out the routing, and what commands I should use. making the app more interesting is much easier from this point.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week11-interface-programming/&quot;&gt;Interface and Application Programming&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on December 02, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Input Devices]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week10-input-devices/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week10-input-devices</id>
  <published>2015-11-25T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-11-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;accelerometer&quot;&gt;Accelerometer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week10/accelerometer.png&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week’s assignment was to measure something - adding a sensor to a microcontroller board that we have designed and read it.&lt;br /&gt;
Still working towards my &lt;a href=&quot;../week1-computer-aided-design/index.html&quot;&gt;final project&lt;/a&gt; I wanted to try and work with a 3d accelerometer, so I can later add one to my smart helmet and use it to detect braking and turn on braking lights.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;board-design&quot;&gt;Board Design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to use both the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.analog.com/media/en/technical-documentation/data-sheets/ADXL343.pdf&quot;&gt;ADXL343&lt;/a&gt; Accelerometer and an RGB LED to show the accelerometer read values.
PA4 and PA6 an the Attiny 44 are SCL and SDA for connecting to the accelerometer.&lt;br /&gt;
For the RGB LED I just made sure I’m using PWM pins (so I’ll be able to program this with Arduino IDE later).&lt;br /&gt;
I also added a FTDI header for calibration and debugging the board, and a battery connector so I can move my small board around, attach it to my bike helmet, etc.&lt;br /&gt;
The ADXL343 needs 3.3V so I’ve added a regulator and calculated the resistors values for the LED the match that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week10/schematics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; My board Eagle schematic&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week10/board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sparkfun/SparkFun-Eagle-Libraries&quot;&gt;Sparkfun’s Eagle libraries&lt;/a&gt; has an ADXL345 lib (in sensor’s category) which I used for the accelerometer. I had to tweak the pads sizes to be able to mill it with a 1/64” endmill.
For doing that:&lt;br /&gt;
- From eagle main screen, locate the part you want to edit and double click on it.&lt;br /&gt;
- This will open the part edit screen.&lt;br /&gt;
- On the left toolbar - press the wrench tool, the choose SMD and choose the desired pad size.&lt;br /&gt;
- click on each pad you need to tweak. rotate and move if needed.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the first iteration I forgot to route the Accelerometer SDA pin to the microcontroller and this took me a while to debug. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;making-the-board&quot;&gt;Making the Board&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process took the longest time this week, which I didn’t expected since I made a bunch of boards before.
The reasons for the long time varied - the milling was not great, since the ADXL 345 pads are really tiny, some of the copper pads fell off the board during the milling.&lt;br /&gt;
I tried using a 0.010” endmill but it broke a few seconds after the milling started.&lt;br /&gt;
I also made the outline file wrong and it removed on of the traces (which I fixed with a jumper wire).&lt;br /&gt;
Some of the issues I found out only later into soldering a wrong milled board, so a big lesson I learned this week was - &lt;strong&gt;Always test the board very very carefully before you start soldering&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week10/boards.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Some of the milled boards I collected this week&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week10/missing_traces.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Missing traces I found out missing only when done soldering&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another big challenge in making the board was soldering the tiny accelerometer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week10/finger.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The accelerometer on my finger - tiny&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neil showed a nice method of doing reflow using the hot air gun, which looks so pretty and simple on &lt;a href=&quot;http://academy.cba.mit.edu/classes/input_devices/accel/hello.ADXL343.reflow.jpg&quot;&gt;this picture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When I tried, it turned out to be a little bit more complicated.&lt;br /&gt;
I shortened the board a few times and did not connect the accelerometer correctly a few times until I learned the exact amount of solder to use and right amount of time to reflow.
I still don’t master this method but I certainly improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One good thing to do is to start with soldering the accelerometer on an empty board, then using a multimeter to test that nothing is shortened before continuing to the other parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each time after I finished soldering a board I tried uploading Neil’s example codes for RGD LED and the ADXL to make sure everything works. most of the times the RGB LED worked perfect but no input from the accelerometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some trial and error, debugging and desoldering, I got a working board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week10/final.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Final board&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;programming-the-board&quot;&gt;Programming the Board&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the making issues I had this week did not leave much time for programming the board and I didn’t get the chance to work on detecting a brake as I originally planned.&lt;br /&gt;
Now that I have the board working though, I’m hoping to get back to this before the final project submission.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead I read the X Y Z values from the Accelerometer and change the RGB color accordingly.
I used  Adafruit’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adafruit/TinyWireM&quot;&gt;TinyWireM library&lt;/a&gt; to read the accelerometer values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week10/green.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week10/blue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week10/yellow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;The LED changing colors according to the board position&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week10-input-devices/&quot;&gt;Input Devices&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on November 25, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Output Devices]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week9-output-devices/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week9-output-devices</id>
  <published>2015-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;light-and-sound&quot;&gt;Light and Sound&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week9/open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week’s assignment was to add an output device to a microcontroller board we’ve designed and program it to do something.&lt;br /&gt;
Since final assignments deadline is getting closer I’m trying to make things that I can use for my &lt;a href=&quot;../week1-computer-aided-design/index.html&quot;&gt;final project&lt;/a&gt; as well.&lt;br /&gt;
I want my smart helmet to have LEDs on it, that will blink when I turn, and also a speaker inside, to give me directions.  So for this week’s assignment I wanted to make a microcontroller board with a speaker and LED Array.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;board-design&quot;&gt;Board Design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve looked at Neil’s designs for &lt;a href=&quot;http://academy.cba.mit.edu/classes/output_devices/array/hello.array.44.2.png&quot;&gt;LED array board&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://academy.cba.mit.edu/classes/output_devices/speaker/hello.speaker.45.png&quot;&gt;speaker board&lt;/a&gt;
And combined them to a new board using Eagle.
I’ve added a button, a jack for power, and a green LED between VCC and ground that is turned on when the board is connected to power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week9/schematic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; My board Eagle schematic&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week9/board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All files for making the board can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasrub/HowToMake/tree/master/files/week9/light_and_sound_board&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LED Array is done using 20 LEDs and only 5 pins with the great &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlieplexing&quot;&gt;Charlieplexing&lt;/a&gt; technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil is using a nice trick in the LED Array to avoid the use of a lot of resistors and keep the board cleaner - 
There are 2 layers to the board, and they are separated with a vinyl-cut epoxy film sticker.
For doing this:&lt;br /&gt;
You first mill the traces of the board as usual.&lt;br /&gt;
Then, you vinyl-cut epoxy film and stick it on top of the board.&lt;br /&gt;
The you vinyl-cut coper and stick it on top of the epoxy film.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;to-create-the-vinyl-cutting-files-in-eagle&quot;&gt;To create the vinyl cutting files in eagle:&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The epoxy-film sticker:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you are done designing the board hit &lt;em&gt;display none tCream&lt;/em&gt;
Then go to view-&amp;gt; Layer settings and click on Change. Choose a solid filling for the tCream objects and export as a monochrome with 600 DPI
I then used Photoshop (But any simple paint software will work) to crop and invert the exported image.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Copper traces on top:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The important thing to remember here is that the vinyl cutter resolution is not the same as the milling machine’s. &lt;strong&gt;Use thicker lines&lt;/strong&gt;. The rest is easy, draw the traces on a different layer (I used bottom since I have the free version of Eagle and it only allows 2 layers) and export this layer only.  Again, invert and crop in any paint software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;making-the-board&quot;&gt;Making the Board&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same process as making boards in the recent weeks. By now I got much better and faster in producing boards :)
(And an LED Array requires A LOT of soldering).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week9/milled_board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; First version of the board milled, you can see that the milling was not great&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week9/sticker.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; putting the epoxy film sticker&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week9/with_copper.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; And the copper traces&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(On the first version of my board I added another black vinyl sticker, just for the color, this was a mistake since the vinyl melts under soldering heat.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week9/stuffed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Stuffed board - second and better version&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;programming-the-board&quot;&gt;Programming the Board&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the fun stage of testing and playing around.
I first tested that each output device works by uploading Neil’s code.
The LED Array was great:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week9/array.gif&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; LED array at action&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speaker was not that simple - when first uploading Neil’s code nothing happened. 
(I suspected this was related to the fact the I used an Atitny 44 while Neil used Attiny 45 but did not succeed in debugging this, The code did compile and uploaded successfully to my board, now I’m thinking this was a power issue and I should test this again with a different power supply).
I then tried using Arduino Tone() library, but still, I heard nothing out of the speaker.&lt;br /&gt;
After some reading around the web, I found &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.media.mit.edu/~leah/LilyPad/07_sound.html&quot;&gt;leah buechley’s code for getting sound from a LilyPad&lt;/a&gt; and this magically worked.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/PyxY3bH1KXU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was still not stable and the speaker would sometimes just click when I pressed to button. That issue eventually resolved by replacing the power supply to higher current (1 amp instead of 0.2). Next time I should add a resistor to the speaker to solve that.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I had a lot of fun playing different 8 bit tunes I found online and composed my self, and lighting the LED’s in different shapes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week9/heart.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; A blinking heart&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week9/arrow_blink.gif&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; A moving arrow I can use on my helmet to signal turning direction&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I experimented with combining the light and sound output - I’ve created random lights that are show with each note of the annoying sound being played :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Foc7ZxowAzc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My code is a combination of Leah’s sound_code and Neil’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://academy.cba.mit.edu/classes/output_devices/array/hello.array.44.2.c&quot;&gt;hello.array.44.2&lt;/a&gt;
And it uses “pitches.h” from the Arduino Tone() Library.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasrub/HowToMake/tree/master/files/week9/light_and_sound&quot;&gt;Get it here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week9-output-devices/&quot;&gt;Output Devices&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on November 13, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Embedded Programming & Networking and Communications]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week8-embedded-programming/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week8-embedded-programming</id>
  <published>2015-11-02T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-11-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week8/open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-1---embedded-programing&quot;&gt;Part 1 - Embedded Programing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-morse-code-receiver-and-transmitter&quot;&gt;A Morse Code Receiver and Transmitter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week’s assignment was to program the board we made &lt;a href=&quot;../week6-electronics-design/index.html&quot;&gt;two weeks ago&lt;/a&gt; to do something, with as many different programming languages and programming environments as possible.&lt;br /&gt;
I wanted to use all the features I have on my board - the button, the LED and the serial port, so I’ve decided to make a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morse_code&quot;&gt;Morse code&lt;/a&gt; receiver and transmitter.&lt;br /&gt;
When the board is connected to the computer, if you type a letter on the computer keyboard, the LED will blink that letter’s Morse code. You can also press the button different combinations of dots and dashes (short and long presses) and the letter you pressed will print on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;programming-the-board-using-arduino-ide&quot;&gt;Programming the Board using Arduino IDE&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&quot;http://highlowtech.org/?p=1695&quot;&gt;this great tutorial&lt;/a&gt; to get the Arduino IDE working with the ATTiny44 that is on my board.&lt;br /&gt;
One very confusing point when programming with both plain C and the Arduino environment is the pins numbers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week8/datasheet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; This is the ATTiny drawing from the &lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://academy.cba.mit.edu/classes/embedded_programming/doc8183.pdf&quot;&gt;datasheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week8/attiny44.png&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; This is the ATTiny drawing from the tutorial &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pin numbers written in the second drawing are the correct one to use in the Arduino IDE.
Since I connected the LED to PA7 and the button to PA3 I used 7 and 3 accordingly.&lt;br /&gt;
Another thing to notice is the clock settings in Arduino. My board has a 20Mhz Crystal on it, so I set the clock to 20Mhz (external) and had to click on “Burn Bootloader” before uploading the sketch to the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week8/choosing_clock.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; choosing the clock &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than that I found it very nice to program the board using the Arduino IDE, thanks to all the libraries that are already written for it and makes a lot of things very simple and abstract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week8/programming.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; programming the board using the programmer I made on &lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../week3-electronics-production/index.html&quot;&gt;week 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sketch itself can be downloaded from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasrub/HowToMake/tree/master/files/week8&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
I used binary numbers to represent to Morse code, in order to save space. 
A dot is represented by 0 and a dash by 1. All letters are sorted in an array and each letter location is it’s Morse code.
Sorting the letters in the array is simple - since Morse letters can be sorted by a &lt;a href=&quot;http://apfelmus.nfshost.com/articles/fun-with-morse-code/morse-tree.png&quot;&gt;binary tree&lt;/a&gt; I just made a string of all the letters in the tree going over each row from left to right, adding question marks instead of empty node in the tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-c&quot; data-lang=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;letters&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;ETIANMSURWDKGOHVF-L?PJBXCYZQ.?54?3???2??+????16=/?????7???8?90?&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting thing is that it uses 3,736 bytes (91%) of program storage space. Maximum is 4,096 bytes. That’s a lot. The main reason is that for serial connection I use SoftwareSerial library, and this takes most of the memory space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;programming-the-board-with-c&quot;&gt;Programming the board with C&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then wanted to create the exact same software in C, and test the memory usage difference.
In C, we use the same pin names as in the datasheet (so PA7 for my led and PA3 for my button).
I wrote the part of receiving letters from the keyboard and blinking Morse code. that worked fine (but took a lot more lines of code). I then needed to write a C implementation for Arduino function “millis()” , to count the elapsed milliseconds in order to get the time the button is pressed. this started to get a little bit too complicated and I left it aside for another time, in order to try and do some networking and communications as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-2---networking-and-communications&quot;&gt;Part 2 - Networking and Communications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week8/all.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this year we are missing the networking and communications week, this was thought in this week’s recitation and was given as a bonus assignment.&lt;br /&gt;
The assignment was to design and build a wired or wireless network connecting at least two processors.&lt;br /&gt;
For my final project, I’m planning to make a smart bicycle helmet, and put buttons on the steering wheel that will turn on turning lights on the helmet. I also want to add a small speaker inside the helmet the could give navigation instructions from a phone. This will require wireless communications between the buttons on the steering wheel and the LEDs in the helmet and also communications between the speaker in the helmet and the phone.&lt;br /&gt;
I figured the best way to connect all the above would be Bluetooth and decided to try and implement a simple communication module this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the HM-10 Bluetooth module, that is explained in &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/doc/tutorials/programming/bluetooth.html&quot;&gt;Thras’s tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week8/bt_module.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BT module should be connected to the FTDI connection that is on my board, but then I had a few issues:
 - The same connection is also supplying the power to the board. 
 - The locations of GND, VCC TX and RX on each board are not similar.&lt;br /&gt;
 - The HM-10 is rated to operate at a supply voltage of 2.0 to 3.7 volts, and its I/O are 3.3V tolerant! The ATtiny is more flexible and has operating voltage of 1.8 - 5.5V.
 - I couldn’t find any female-female cables around the electronics shop and had to think of a creative way to connect the BT and the board. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some thinking, Thras advised that I’ll make a board that connects the two parts and also supply power. So this is what I did, I also added a 3.3V Regulator to that board for the BT.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week8/bt_2_traces.png&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Traces for my small connecting board &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week8/stuffed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; connecting board stuffed &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have two boards connected to BT modules. hurray!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week8/building_network.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now comes programming the communication part.
For testing, I used the code from &lt;a href=&quot;http://arduinofy.blogspot.com/2013/05/attiny-bluetooth.html&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;
changing RxD to 0, TxD to 1, and the led pin to 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can now control the LED on the board by sending 0 or 1 from my computer, via Bluetooth, that’s very exciting! :)  I’ll continue to work on this on the following week, to be able to press the button in one board to light the LED on the other.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week8/bt_working.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Success. LED on board powered via Bluetooth &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week8-embedded-programming/&quot;&gt;Embedded Programming &amp; Networking and Communications&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on November 02, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Molding and Casting]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week7-molding-and-casting/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week7-molding-and-casting</id>
  <published>2015-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week’s assignment was to design a 3D mold, machine it, and cast parts from it.&lt;br /&gt;
As a ceramic design student, I have vast experience in mold making.&lt;br /&gt;
I’ve made a lot a plaster molds, used for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slipcasting&quot;&gt;ceramic slipcasting&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve also made many silicon molds for different plastics, plasters, and wax mold for glass casting.&lt;br /&gt;
I’ve never designed a mold using CAD tools. I found out that this is a more complicated process than what I expected.&lt;br /&gt;
Saying that, this new option of making CAD molds was really exciting and I’m sure I’ll use this method again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this was a very busy week for me as an RA, I decided to make something simple - a homage to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sheilazellerinteriors.com/articles/the-black-house-bird&quot;&gt;Eames famous house bird&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/eames_bird.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The Eames black house bird &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Rhino for designing the mold. Modeling the bird itself was quite simple. I separated the bird’s legs from the body, planning to glue them to the bird later, or using metal wires as legs instead.&lt;br /&gt;
After the bird was complete I added a cutting plane in its center, in a size little bit smaller than the piece of wax we got, leaving some room for walls. I then also added keys (half spheres, added to one side and  excluded from the other). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/rhino.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Designing with Rhino &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;machining-the-model-for-molding&quot;&gt;Machining the model for molding&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a few mistakes in my design - I wanted to make the bird as big as I can, this made my walls too thin, and some of them were lost in the milling. Also, I’ve made the keys too small, not considering the end mill size, and they were barely seen on the wax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/milling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Milling the piece of wax &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked with PartWorks 3D for making the toolpaths for milling the mold. I wanted to fit the 2 sides of my bird on the same piece of wax. In the software there is no option of adding 2 stl files for one toolpath, nor  option for manually setting the origin of the model inside the material, The program automatically locates the model in the center of the material.&lt;br /&gt;
I solved this issue by setting the material width in the program to be half of the width of my real material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/one_side.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; First side done &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/milling_done.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Two sides done. I lost 3 walls in the process &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;making-the-mold&quot;&gt;Making the mold&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used cardboard pieces instead of the missing walls. I used putty to make a spout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/ready_for_mold.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Ready for mold making &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then just poured Oomoo on it and left it for the night. (Oomoo is the silicon we used for mold making).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/oomoo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Oomoo &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mold released quickly and easily and came out nice, except for one small bubble on the bird’s head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/molds.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Finished Oomoo molds &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;casting&quot;&gt;Casting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the keys on my mold were too small, it was really hard to hold the two parts of the mold together correctly, and I decided to first cast each part separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/ready_for_cast.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Ready for casting &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/casting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Casting dryStone in two parts of the mold &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When taking the cast out, the bird legs were too thin and broke immediately. the bird’s body parts were a bit stronger but still broke when I pressed them too hard together. I’ll cast more parts when I have some free time (this is the fun things about molds - you can cast many parts out of one mold).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/cast.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, when looking just on one half, it’s not that similar to the Eames house bird, but I still really like the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week7/done.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week7-molding-and-casting/&quot;&gt;Molding and Casting&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on October 28, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Electronics Design]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week6-electronics-design/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week6-electronics-design</id>
  <published>2015-10-20T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-10-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week’s assignment was to redraw the echo hello-world board, add a button and LED to it, and make it.&lt;br /&gt;
Since I don’t have any experience with electronics before, this week involved a lot of reading and learning. I do feel I had A LOT of progress in my electronics understanding since the beginning of this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/learning.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Learning electronics &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;designing-the-board&quot;&gt;Designing The Board&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cadsoftusa.com/&quot;&gt;Eagle&lt;/a&gt; for redrawing the board.
First, I added all the components from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://academy.cba.mit.edu/classes/embedded_programming/hello.ftdi.44.png&quot;&gt;original board drawing&lt;/a&gt; and then I connected them following the board traces.
I then added one LED from VCC to Ground, that will light when the board is connected to power (this should be an indication that the board is routed ok).&lt;br /&gt;
I added another LED to PA7 I/O pin of the ATTiny44 and a button to PA3, so I can later program their behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/schematics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The board schematic &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After designing the schematics comes the hard part of routing the board.&lt;br /&gt;
This felt like and endless puzzle. Every connection I made got in the way of another connection. Eventually I added one jumper to solve my puzzle.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/routing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Final board drawing &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/traces.png&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The traces I used. I added my initials using Photoshop &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;making-the-board&quot;&gt;Making the board&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First I had to mill to board. since we already did this a few weeks ago, I was already familiar with the fab modules and the Roland mill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/milling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Milling machine at work &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/milled_board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Milled board &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I had to stuff the board with components, I wanted to use a 300-380Ω resistor for connecting the LEDs, since there were no such resistors in the CBA shop I put 499Ω on top of a 1kΩ, so they are in parallel, then the value is  &lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/eq.png&quot; alt=&quot;equation&quot; /&gt; =~ 330Ω
When soldering the board, I soldered the FTDI connector wrong, and when trying to de-solder it I accidentally also removed the copper trace that connected it’s VCC pin to the board.&lt;br /&gt;
I decided that before making the board all over again, I’ll try to fix it with a hack. so I connected a wire from the FTDI pin to the VCC wire trace. surprisingly that worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/final_board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Final board &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/wire_hack.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; My wire hack &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then wanted to test my board.
First I connected it to the power supply (my laptop) and the VCC -&amp;gt; GND LED lighted up. This was a very happy moment! :)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/success.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Success! &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I also connected it the programmer I made in week 3 and programmed it using &lt;a href=&quot;http://academy.cba.mit.edu/classes/embedded_programming/hello.ftdi.44.program.png&quot;&gt;these instructions&lt;/a&gt;. That also worked well, and confirmed my board is working fine. I did not test the LED an button that are connected to the microcontroler yet. I’ll do that in embedded programming week (which is week 8)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week6/programming.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Programming the board &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week6-electronics-design/&quot;&gt;Electronics Design&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on October 20, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Computer-Controlled Machining]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week5-computer-controlled-machining/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week5-computer-controlled-machining</id>
  <published>2015-10-13T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-10-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;legged-hexagon-table&quot;&gt;3 Legged Hexagon Table&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week’s assignment was to make something big.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to make a nice dining table for my apartment.&lt;br /&gt;
I thought this would be a great opportunity to learn Solidworks and improve my CAD skills. It was important for me to keep my design parametric, so if I buy nicer wood with different thickness I could just change the thickness variable and cut the same design, I also wanted to be able to scale the table easily, or just change the hieght or diameter if I wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/complete_design.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The table top &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/leg_side_view.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Side view of the leg and support &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/side_view.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The table is constructed from four different parts: the hexagon table top, the legs, support piece for each leg and a small triangle that sits in the hole in the middle of the table top.
In order to keep the table top as clean and as smooth as possible, I designed pockets in the lower side of the table top that are exactly the size of the table legs, so the table legs sit in those pockets, but are not seen on the table top, for it to sit exactly and not move, there is a this slot in each pocket, and a thin part on top of each leg (made by pocketing) that fits inside the slot. tha small triangle keeps everything together.&lt;br /&gt;
The legs also fit together with the help of pockets in the intersection lines, so the can be as tight as possible with only the small triangle space between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;toolpathing&quot;&gt;Toolpathing:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learned how to use the ShopBot and got a 4’ X 8’ OSB sheet, 7/16” thick.
The OSB is not a fun material, there were a lot of splinters around and in my hands. But except the splinters the milling came out good and accurate and the pockets looked good. 
I am planning to buy nice wood and cut this again, so this time I’ll cut thing right. (and update this page with pictures of the nice table). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/mirrored_legs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The dxf file ready for toolpathing. Red is for pocketing, purple for cutting inside and green for cutting outside &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cutting&quot;&gt;Cutting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My design has slots for half of the material thickness (that pocketed parts fit in), these slots are 7/32” wide, so I could not make them with th 1/4” endmill.
Since the rest of the cuts could be made with the bigger endmill, I first cut everything with 1/4” endmill and then changed the endmill to 1/8” and cut the thin slots. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/toolpath.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;  The toolpath ready for cut&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/machine_working.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The ShopBot cutting my part&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The board ready &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;constructing&quot;&gt;Constructing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a mistake while making the toolpath and mirrored 2 of the tables legs (explained more detailed at the notes of this post). Due to lack of time and material to cut new parts, I had to use wood glue and clamps to hold the parts together:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/building.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/building2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I let the glue dry for 24 and this is the result:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/done.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week5/with_cup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Cup on table to demonstrate the size. Each hexagon side is 23&quot;, the table hight is 29&quot; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all I’m happy with this table. I’m more happy that I learned a lot, both about working with Solidworks and parameters, and also about toolpathing and machining in general. I keep thinking of other things I now want and able to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I learned a very important lesson during the toolpathing and cutting part: when making the toolpath for the cut, I was not thinking two much, and mirrored two on the legs to fit nicer on the sheet. since my design is not completely symmetrical (there are slots with 0.25” thickness, that pocketed parts go inside), the mirrored legs did not fit. since I did not have time and enough material to cut 2 new legs, I cut another mirrored one and made the desk by sanding parts in the legs that did not fit and gluing everything together instead of using the slots for construction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During my online search for inspirations I ran into the really cool &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opendesk.cc&quot;&gt;Opendesk&lt;/a&gt; website. Which is a global platform for local making. They have beautiful open source furniture designs that inspired my design a lot and gave me great ideas for the joints.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Note that it’s very important where you put tabs, not inside slots! (luckily I learned that when cutting test parts for checking slots width.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expect to spend much more time on design when working with a new tool. Working with Solidworks took much longer then I planned to achieve the desired results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week5-computer-controlled-machining/&quot;&gt;Computer-Controlled Machining&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on October 13, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[3D Scanning and Printing]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week4-3d-printing-and-scanning/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week4-3d-printing-and-scanning</id>
  <published>2015-10-05T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-10-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;designing-and-3d-printing&quot;&gt;Designing and 3D Printing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first assignment of this week was to design and 3D print an object that could not be made subtractively.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was Inspired by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simplydifferently.org/Helix_Zome&quot;&gt;Helix Zome&lt;/a&gt; , that was developed by &lt;a href=&quot;http://heliss.com/&quot;&gt;Nicolas Causse&lt;/a&gt; in 2006. The term Zome comes from “zonohedron” + “dome” and is often used for unusual dome variants.
The fun thing is, that one of the ways of describing the helix zome is parametric, so I could, with a few changes, to model the zome using Rhino and Grasshopper.
In the original idea, since this is used as a zome, the helixes go from 0 to Pi. I wanted to create an egg shape, which is actually two zomes, so in my design α = -π .. π &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/gh_script.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/python_code.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;The Grasshopper script and python code that create the model&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;!-- &lt;video width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;240&quot; autoplay&gt; --&gt;
	&lt;video autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    	&lt;source src=&quot;../images/week4/movie.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
		Your browser does not support the video tag.
	&lt;/video&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Animation of completed basic model&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then added more modifications - Creating a small zome inside the zome, and making a zome from single helixes (removing the second for loop from the code).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My grasshopper scripts can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jasrub/HowToMake/tree/master/files/week4&quot;&gt;downloaded here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;printing&quot;&gt;Printing&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve printed the three variations of the zome to test different printing options and parameters.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;a-zome-inside-a-zome&quot;&gt;A Zome Inside a Zome&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve created a model of a small zome (30 mm diameter) inside a bigger zome (70 mm diameter), not connected.
I’ve sent this .stl file to Tom at the CBA shop, to be printed by the Dimension 3D printer.&lt;br /&gt;
The Dimension hase the advantage of printing a support material that is different from the printed material, and so I used this to print the complete model of the zome with the small zome inside - all in one piece.&lt;br /&gt;
This could not be done using the ultimaker.&lt;br /&gt;
This model is very complex and required a lot of support material. the printing took 20 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/dimension_printing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The Dimension printer printing my model. You can&#39;t see much, just a lot of support material &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/zome_inside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Final result - The Zome Rattle &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/zoom_small_zome.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Zoom in on the small zome &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;the-double-helix-zome&quot;&gt;The Double Helix Zome&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to try and print with the Ultimaker 2. since the complete zome does not have a base, I would have needed a lot of support material to be printed, which would have make the print very long, and also I would had a lot of work after printing, cleaning the model.
In order to solve this issue, I cut the model in the middle, and printed each half separately. This way I could print with no support at all and it took a few seconds to glue the two parts after the print was finished. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/cura.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The two halves ready for print &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a little glitch in one of the prints. There was a small part that moved not long after the print started. but the Ultimaker managed to continue the print normally and I’m only left with this small print error on my model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/printer_at_work.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Beginning of the print &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/printing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Printing &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/double_zome_half.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Finished half on the printer bed &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/double_zome_half2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/print_error.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Completed model &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;the-single-helix-zome&quot;&gt;The Single Helix Zome&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After these two prints came out successfully I decided to print a smaller zome, with single helix, which has a more interesting shape (in my opinion).&lt;br /&gt;
I used the same technique as in the previous print with the Ultimaker - printing two halves and then gluing them together.
This print is my favorite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/halves_single_zome.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Two halves &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/single_zome2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The single zome &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/all_zomes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The three zomes &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also used this model for another assignment I had this week.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EfQID5LcnuA&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; is a short movie documenting the design and print process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;d-scanning&quot;&gt;3D Scanning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second assignment of this week was to 3D scan an object, and optionally print it.
I’ve tried 3D scanning before with different DIY methods - 123D catch app and a kinect sensor, and was never quite happy with the result.
I tried using the Sense scanner to scan my ear, but too many details were missing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the fall is coming to Cambridge, there are lots of pine cones outside my house, and I really love pine cones. I decided to try and scan one with the NextEngine 2020i Scanner, that has 0.005” resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/pine_cone_on_scannar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; scanning the small pine cone. I&#39;ve made a base for the pine cone using hot glue so I could scan it in standing position and it did not move &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used MeshLab to smooth and reconstruct the scanned model (Poisson Reconstruction, with the following parameters: Octree Depth - 11, Solver Divide - 7, Sample per Node - 1 and Surface offsetting - 1).&lt;br /&gt;
I used Rhino to make a flat base for the pine cone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/meshlab.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/rhino.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Refining the model using MeshLab and Rhino&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I printed the finished model on the Ultimaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/pine_cone_model.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The printed scan &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week4/pine_and_model.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; The printed model near the original pine cone&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results this time were surprisingly good!  &lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week4-3d-printing-and-scanning/&quot;&gt;3D Scanning and Printing&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on October 05, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Electronics Production]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week3-electronics-production/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week3-electronics-production</id>
  <published>2015-09-29T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-09-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;my-first-circuit-board&quot;&gt;My First Circuit Board&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week3/open2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assignment this week was to make the FabISP in-circuit programmer.&lt;br /&gt;
I’ve never dealt with electronics before, so I was a bit intimidated with this assignment.&lt;br /&gt;
I Decided to work very slowly, step by step, to make sure I understand and do everything correctly.&lt;br /&gt;
I followed &lt;a href=&quot;http://fabacademy.org/archives/content/tutorials/05_Electronics_Production/Assemble_and_Program_FabISP.html&quot;&gt;this great tutorial&lt;/a&gt; which was very helpful. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time, after I finished stuffing the board with all components, I got an error saying I should double check connection and try again. After triple checking all connections and soldering with the help of Thras, our TA, we got to a conclusion that there is probably something wrong with the attiny44 chip, and it would be best if I just make a new board from scratch.&lt;br /&gt;
I think this was a great decision. The second board took me less then half of the time to make, it came out prettier and worked perfectly. And also, most imporantly, I feel much more confident about my soldering skills now.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;making-the-board&quot;&gt;Making the board:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;milling&quot;&gt;Milling&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is milling the board.&lt;br /&gt;
This is pretty simple. I just had to load the settings, that were already on the computer in the shop, to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://fabmodules.org/&quot;&gt;fab modules&lt;/a&gt;. I used a new mill head so I changed the speed to 3.7 mm/s and the cut depth to 0.12 mm.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week3/milling_machine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Milling machine at work &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my second board I changed the number of offsets to -1 in order cut everything but the traces, this took about 6 minutes more for milling, but preffer it since I think it looks cleaner, and is easier to debug that way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week3/first_board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week3/second-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;First board on the left, 4 offsets.  Second board on the right, filled.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;soldering&quot;&gt;Soldering&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After milling comes the hard part - soldering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week3/soldering.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt; Solder iron and my board &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week3/first-steps.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;First steps&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week3/first-board-soldered.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;First Board Soldered&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week3/second_board_soldered.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Second Board Soldered - The Soldering here is much nicer &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;testing-and-programming-the-board&quot;&gt;Testing and Programming The Board&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last step is connecting the board to the computer an program it to be a programmer.&lt;br /&gt;
As mentioned, in my first attempt, this did not go well. I get blinking orange light on the ATAVRISP2 Programmer, which means something is wrong with my connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week3/testing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Orange light on the ATAVRISP2 Programmer&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the second attempt this went great. I got green light on my first try.
After programming my programmer I removed the jumpers, and - voilà!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week3/last.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Finished board with the first board behind.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week3-electronics-production/&quot;&gt;Electronics Production&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on September 29, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Computer-Controlled Cutting]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week2-computer-controlled-cutting/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week2-computer-controlled-cutting</id>
  <published>2015-09-22T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-09-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;modular-honeycomb-shelves&quot;&gt;Modular Honeycomb Shelves&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assignment this week was to design, make, and document a press-fit construction kit.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently moved to a new apartment and wanted to make some nice storage solution that
will be both pretty and functional.
My inspiration was the geometric simple design and infinity of honeycombs.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve used Rhino and Grasshopper to create the basic shapes the build hexagon boxes that can then build a honeycomb-like wall storage.&lt;br /&gt;
My Grasshopper script gets as inputs the desired length of the hexagon sides, the thickness of the cardboard, and the laser offset. It is then outputs 3 shapes that I can send for printing (laser cutting)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The settings I’ve used with the Epilog laser cutter and given cardboard:&lt;br /&gt;
speed: 25-29%&lt;br /&gt;
power: 70-75%&lt;br /&gt;
frequency: 25000&lt;br /&gt;
Carbboard thickness: 4 mm  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week2/design.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Planning with Rhino and Grasshopper&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic unit is made out of the base hexagon, that can connect with other base hexagons and creates the tiling; The squares, that connect to the base hexagon and create the walls; And the back part, which binds the whole part together and also has holes so it can be hanged on the wall.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve set the length parameter in my model to be 10cm, the fun thing is that I can now change this parameter and create the honeycomb shelves any size I’de like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week2/cut.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Laser cutting the parts&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week2/pieces.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;All parts, ready to be assembled&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week2/connecting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week2/construction.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;connecting the pieces&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week2/hanging.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Hanging on the wall&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week2/finished_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Final result&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vinyl-cutting-fun&quot;&gt;Vinyl Cutting Fun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also got to play with the Vinyl Cutter machine this week.
I’ve made some fun stickers :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week2/Vinyl1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week2/vinyl2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week2-computer-controlled-cutting/&quot;&gt;Computer-Controlled Cutting&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on September 22, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Computer Aided Design]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week1-computer-aided-design/" />
  <id>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week1-computer-aided-design</id>
  <published>2015-09-21T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-09-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jasmin Rubinovitz</name>
    <uri>http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz</uri>
    <email>jasrub@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;final-project-idea---a-smart-helmet&quot;&gt;Final Project Idea - a Smart Helmet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first assignment was to model possible final project.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commute mainly with bike, so my idea for the final project is a smart bicycle helmet.&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week1/bike_clipart.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt;    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to make a helmet that is controlled both from your phone and also from buttons on the handle bar.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The helmet will have a front light and back lights, and you can turn on signal lights when making turns.&lt;br /&gt;
It will also have an inside speaker, so you can listen to navigation instructions from you phone while riding.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Rhino for modeling and rendering the desiered helmet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img align=&quot;center&quot; src=&quot;../images/week1/helmet_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;First steps of modeling&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img align=&quot;center&quot; src=&quot;../images/week1/helmet_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the results:
&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week1/render_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week1/render_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week1/render_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;../images/week1/render_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz/week1-computer-aided-design/&quot;&gt;Computer Aided Design&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Jasmin Rubinovitz at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fab.cba.mit.edu/classes/863.15/section.CBA/people/Rubinovitz&quot;&gt;Jasmin Rubinovitz&lt;/a&gt; on September 21, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>